A Guide to the William Gordon McCabe Papers, 1757-1920
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
William Gordon McCabe Papers 1757-1920
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10568
This collection contains ca. 1,016 items (7 Hollinger boxes; ca. 2.3 linear shelf feet).
The papers consist chiefly of William McCabe's correspondence with prominent scholars, U.S. and British literary figures, and Civil War veterans. Topics include the Civil War, the Confederacy, Confederate veterans organizations, World War I, black suffrage, the University of Virginia, and British literature.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Provenance
The William Gordon McCabe Papers were placed on loan in the Library by Mrs. WilliamGordon McCabe, Jr. of Greenville, South Carolina, on November 1, 1984. They were made a gift on February 29, 1984.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Gordon McCabe was born on August 4, 1841, in Richmond, Virginia, the son of the Rev. John Collins and Sophia Gordon (nee Taylor). After graduating from Hampton Academy in 1858 he became a tutor for the Selden family of "Westover." He graduated from the University of Virginia in 1861 and later received honorary degrees from a number of institutions, including: Master of Arts degree, 1868, and Doctor of Laws degree in 1906 from the College of William and Mary; a Master of Arts degree from Williams College in 1885; and a Doctor of Letters degree from Yale in 1897. McCabe served in the Confederate Army during the Civil War, eventually rising to the rank of captain of artillery in the Army of Northern Virginia under the command of Colonel William Johnson Pegram. After being paroled in 1865 he founded University School in Petersburg, Virginia; it was eventually moved to Richmond.
He remained its principal until he retired in 1901 and closed the school. McCabe served on the Board of Visitors at the University of Virginia, 1888-1892, and as vice-rector, 1892-1896. He was associated with various organizations during his lifetime including: the Virginia Historical Society, the Society of the Cincinnati in Virginia, Sons of the American Revolution, Descendants of the Signers of the Declaration of Independence, the American Philological Society of the Modern Language Association, the Virginia Gettysburg Monument Commission, Pegram Battalion Veteran Association, the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, the Head-Masters' Association of America, Phi Beta Kappa, the University Club, the Westmoreland Club, and the Southern Historical Association. He also served as Commissioner and Director of the Jamestown Exposition. McCabe was a frequent traveler and was well known as a speaker and author. He was the editor of various works of poetry and essays, and he published several original books including: A Grammar of the Latin Language, 1884; Latin Reader; Caesar's Gallic War, 1886; Virginia Schools Before and After the Revolution, 1890; and Memoir of Joseph Bryan, 1903. He was married to June Pleasants Harrison Osborne on April 12, 1867, and had three sons: Edmund Osborne, William Gordon, Jr., and Edward Raynsford Warner. After his wife's death, he married Gillie Armistead Cary on March 16, 1915. McCabe died on June l, 1920, at age seventy-eight.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 1,016 items (7 Hollinger boxes; ca. 2.3 linear shelf feet), l757-l896 and l836-l920, chiefly letters to William Gordon McCabe (l841-1920), author, educator, and a member of the Board of Visitors at the University of Virginia. The collection also contains a few newspaper clippings, printed material, genealogical material, memorabilia and other related papers. Some of the letters are addressed to persons other than McCabe and there are a few letters written by him. Topics of interest in the letters include: the University of Virginia, the Civil War, the Confederacy, Confederate veterans organizations, the destruction of Hampton, Virginia in l861, education in Virginia, Negro suffrage, World War I, life in the 3l8th Virginia Infantry, 2nd Battalion, 80th Division during l9l8, Latin studies, Egypt in l9l6, Swedenborgianism, Einstein's Theory of Relativity, and British literature. Due to his literary and scholarly activities, McCabe was acquainted and corresponded with prominent individuals in Europe and America. The names of these correspondents may be learned from the list of folder headings that forms part of this guide. Letters by the following individuals may be found in the folders headed "Miscellaneous": William Noland Berkeley, William Edgar Borah, Philip Alexander Bruce, James Lawrence Cabell, Noah K. Davis, Westmoreland Davis, Chauncey M. Depew, William Everett, Charles W. Kent, Thomas S. Martin, George H. Moses, Beverley Bland Munford, John M. Page, John S. Patton, William Peters, W.C.N. Randolph, Maximilian R. Schele de Vere, Henry C. Stuart, Claude A. Swanson, William P. Trent, Anna Seeley Tuttle, Charles S. Venable, and Richard M. Venable.
The collection also contains carbon copies of transcripts of a few letters for which originals are not present. These include: an l836 letter from Edgar Allan Poe, as editor of the Southern Literary Messenger, to the Rev. Dr. John Collins McCabe; an l874 Robert Browning letter to Ann Thackery [Anne Isabella Thackeray Ritchie?]; three 1884 Henry James letters to McCabe; and letters from Robert E. Lee, Benjamin Franklin, and Thomas Jefferson. Other persons represented by miscellaneous items in the collection include: Joseph H. Choate, Basil L. Gildersleeve, John Richard Green, Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson, Catesby Ap Roger Jones, Philip W. McKinney, Fitzhugh Lee, William Charles Macready, Thomas R. Price, Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy, and George Taylor. Taylor was a signer of the Declaration of Independence and McCabe's great- great grandfather through his mother, Sophia Gordon Taylor. His papers, 1757-1796, consist of letters, including two from Charles Stewart and Joseph Galloway, both members of the Continental Congress, and several papers pertaining to his financial and legal activities in Easton, Pennsylvania. Items of interest in the collection include: a scholarship medal awarded to McCabe from Hampton Academy in 1857; an autograph book; a 19ll replica struck from the "Great Seal" of the Confederate States of America; a list of books and manuscripts from his library, some of which were donated to the University of Virginia; copies of class rolls from his University School, commissions appointing McCabe to the Board of Visitors; accounts of his visits at the home of Alfred Lord Tennyson; a l9ll letter of introduction for him to the Archbishop of Canterbury; and three pages from the manuscript of William M. Thackeray's The Virginians. There is a considerable amount of correspondence pertaining to the University of Virginia and its faculty and staff. Topics discussed include: a proposed degree program requirement changes; the replacement of books lost in the Rotunda fire of 1895; the illness of Professor John B. Minor as it related to the survival of the Law School; the resignation of William Howard Perkinson as the result of an anonymous letter claiming his activities injured "Dr. S." (Maxmilliam R. Schele de Vere?) both professionally and financially; and other related matters.
Organization
The collection is divided into two series: I. Main Files and II. Miscellaneous. Series I contains folders of letters and related papers from individuals and organizations which are arranged alphabetically by the name of the correspondent. Series II is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Main Files
  - Charles Francis Adams 1911, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Matthew Arnold 1884-1892, 1905, 10 items (Box 1)
  - Charles Wesley Bain 1872, 1888, 1895, 1902, 1903, 5 items (Box 1)
  - Thomas Willing Balch 1919, 3 items (Box 1)
  - Francis C.B. Barnum 1916-1919, 23 items (Box 1)
  - Charles Beaman 1894-1900, 9 items (Box 1)
  - John Bigelow, Jr. 1911, 1 item (Box 1)
  - William Black 1889-1892, 9 items (Box 1)
  - Frederick Godfrey Bird 1915-1920, 6 items (Box 1)
  - Boyle 1900-1920, 26 items (Box 1)
  - William L. Boyle 1904, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Thomas Stewart Bryan 1920, 1 item (Box 1)
  - John A. Bryce 1885, n.d., 2 items (Box 1)
  - Charles J. Cabaniss 1872, 1882, 1893-1897, 7 items (Box 1)
  - Andrew Carnegie 1910, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Churchill Gibson Chamberlayne 1906, 1 item (Box 1)
  - M. Churchill 1920, 3 items (Box 1)
  - Civil War 1894, 1897, 1919, 4 items (Box 1)
  - Colleges and Universities 1860-1920, 19 items (Box 1)
  - Confederate Memorials 1908, 1919, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Confederate States Veterans 1882-1920, 31 items (Box 2)
  - Dabney 1892, 1913-1919, 6 items (Box 2)
  - Jefferson and Varina Davis 1868, 1896, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Descendants of the Signers of the Declaration of Independence 1902, 1908, 1911, 1919, 6 items (Box 2)
  - Frederick Stoever Dickson 1914, 3 items (Box 2)
  - Mrs. Jubal A. Early 1907, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Sir I.A. Ewing 1904-1905, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Worthington C. Ford 1910, 1915-1916, 4 items (Box 2)
  - Anatole France 1903, 1 item (Box 2)
  - Basil Gildersleeve 1915, 1 item (Box 2)
  - Armistead C. Gordon 1902-1920, 7 items (Box 2)
  - Governors, Senators, and Judges 189401895, 1904-1910, 1919, 1920, 13 items (Box 2)
  - Alice S. Green 1903-1907, 8 items (Box 2)
  - Fairfax Harrison 1916-1920, 7 items (Box 2)
  - Henry Heth 1875, 1891, 3 items (Box 2)
  - Arthur Hill 1903-1908, 4 items (Box 2)
  - Oliver Wendell Holmes 1896, 1905, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Henry Holt 1906, 1 item (Box 2)
  - Leigh Hunt 1869, 1 item (Box 2)
  - Lawrence Hutton 1900, 1 item (Box 2)
  - Thomas J. "Stonewall" and Mary Ann Jackson 1896, 1909, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Thomas Jefferson 1896, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Bradley T. Johnson 1891, 1 item (Box 2)
  - Joseph E. Johnston 1861, 1887, 3 items (Box 2)
  - William Preston Johnston 1870, 1890, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Catesby ap Roger Jones 1876, 1 item (Box 2)
  - Robert E. Lee 1844, 1847, 1862, 1870, 1911, 5 items (Box 2)
  - Lee Family Papers 1898, 1911-1918, 1923, 5 items (Box 2)
  - Henry Cabot Lodge 1911, 1 item (Box 2)
  - William Loring 1890, 1900, 3 items (Box 2)
  - Edmund Osborne McCabe 1928, 2 items (Box 2)
  - William Gordon McCabe: Letters post 1861 - 1920, n.d., 42 items (Box 2)
  - William Gordon McCabe: Miscellaneous 1857, 1865-1920, n.d., 31 items (Box 3)
  - William Gordon McCabe, Jr.: Miscellaneous Letters 1917, 1920, 5 items (Box 3)
  - William Gordon McCabe, Jr.: Letters of Sympathy re the death of his father 1920, 53 items (Box 3)
  - Randolph Harrison McKim 1912-1918, 4 items (Box 3)
  - William Charles Macready 1847, 1 item (Box 3)
  - Julie Magruder 1899-1903, 9 items (Box 3)
  - Sir William Markby 1896-1897, 2 items (Box 3)
  - Maurice Family 1915, 1919-1920, 8 items (Box 3)
  - Dabney Herndon Maury 1885, 1895, 2 items (Box 3)
  - General E.W.L. May 1906, 1910, 3 items (Box 3)
  - Herman C. Merivale 1889, 1 item (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1907, 1908, 1914, n.d., 10 items (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Letters: A-B 1870-1920, 37 items (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Letters: C-F 1864-1920, 40 items (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Letters: G-M 1876-1920, 60 items (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Letters: N-T 1867-1920, 51 items (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Letters: U-Z 1892-1920, 24 items (Box 4)
  - Frederick William Neve 1919, 1 item (Box 4)
  - Betty Page n.d., 1 item (Box 4)
  - Comte de Paris 1890, 1 item (Box 4)
  - Robert Lewis Parrish 1912-1915, 4 items (Box 4)
  - Thomas R. Price 1903-1905 (Box 4)
    Letters and items pertaining to him
  - Publishers 1895-1899, 1909, 1920, 6 items (Box 4)
  - Rev. Alfred Magill Randolph 1904, 1 item (Box 4)
  - Ann Thackeray Ritchie 1884-1891, 16 items (Box 5)
  - Ritchie Family Letters 1919-1920, 9 items (Box 5)
  - John C. Ropes 1887, 1894-1899, 13 items (Box 5)
  - Mildred Lewis Rutherford 1920, 1 item (Box 5)
  - Charles Forester Smith 1908-1909, 2 items (Box 5)
  - William Waugh Smith 1884-1885, 3 items (Box 5)
  - Yates Snowden 1892, 1910, 1914, 3 items (Box 5)
  - Society of the Cincinnati: Virginia 1914 (Box 5)
  - Sons of the American Revolution 1902-1920, 32 items (Box 5)
  - Edmund Clarence Stedman 1885, 1892, 3 items (Box 5)
  - Albert Stickney 1900-1908, 5 items (Box 5)
  - Sulgrave Institution Board of Governors, U.S.A. 1919-1920, 7 items (Box 5)
  - Earl Gregg Swem 1917, 1919, 3 items (Box 5)
  - William Swinton 1872-1873, 2 items (Box 5)
  - George Taylor: Letters, Financial and Legal Papers 1757-1777, Folder 1 of 2, 26 items (Box 5)
  - George Taylor: Letters, Financial and Legal Papers 1778-1796, Folder 2 of 2, 21 items (Box 6)
  - Alfred Tennyson 1884-1889, 5 items (Box 6)
  - Hallam Tennyson 1887, 1889, 1892, 1912, 1914, 7 items (Box 6)
  - John Reuben Thompson 1866, 2 items (Box 6)
  - William M. Thornton 1889-1904, 17 items (Box 6)
  - Bishop Beverley D. Tucker 1899-1909, 1916, 7 items (Box 6)
  - Lyon G. Tyler 1907-1908, 1915-1919, 13 items (Box 6)
  - University of Virginia 1871-1919, 33 items (Box 6)
  - Venerable 1882-1919, 11 items (Box 6)
  - Virginia Historical Society and Families 1874, 1890, 1902, 1907, 1914-1915, 1919, 7 items (Box 6)
  - Virginia State Library Board Nomination 1919, 31 items (Box 6)
  - Harold Wainless 1915-1919, 25 items (Box 6)
  - Sir Spencer Wapole 1904, 1 item (Box 6)
  - Ethan Allen Weaver 1896, 1908-1920, 7 items (Box 6)
  - William H. Welch 1896-1920, 25 items (Box 6)
  - Jennings C. Wise 1918-1920, 8 items (Box 7)
  - John S. Wise 1907-1908, 4 items (Box 7)
  - Owen Wister 1906, 1 item (Box 7)
  - Katharine Pearson Woods 1905, 2 items (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  - Class Rolls of McCabe's University School [1865-1901] (Box 7)
  - The Old Virginia Gentleman, by George W. Bagby 1877 Mar 19 (Box 7)
  - Autograph Book of William Gordon McCabe 1905-1908 (Box 7)
  - List of works in WGM's library donate to the University of Virginia 1922 (Box 7)
  - Copies of papers belonging to WGM ca. 1922 (Box 7)
  - Replica of the Great Seal of the Confederacy 1911 (Othertype 28)
  - Address book of WGM 1920 (Box 7)